William W. Edgerton Civil War Letters
University of Houston Libraries
William W. Edgerton Civil War Letters
1862-1865
Edgerton, William W.
William Wilberforce Edgerton served as a private with the 107th New York Volunteers during the American Civil War, participating in the battles of Antietam, Chancellorsville, and Gettysburg. He enlisted in 1862 and was honorably discharged on June 18, 1865. The collection consists primarily of correspondence from Edgerton to his mother, brother, and sisters.
2 boxes; 154 items, .8 linear feet
1955-001
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
William Wilberforce Edgerton was born August 4, 1845 in Waverly, New York to Dorothy Doud and John Leffingwell Edgerton. He was the third of four children, two older sisters and one younger brother. At the age of twelve he left home to live on his own due to the break-up of his family. His father was a traveling lecturer and teacher and was away much of the time. His younger brother lived with his sister Martha and her husband, and his mother moved in with friends in Sparta, Wisconsin, during the Civil War.
Edgerton survived on his own by his wits and succession of small jobs. He spent some time "peddling" but found it a poor way to make a living. He tried harness making, bar tending, and eventually even spent some time working at a race track. By the age of seventeen he found himself working as a blacksmith's apprentice. After a couple of setbacks of the Union forces and a major campaign for new recruits by President Lincoln, Edgerton decided to join the Union Army, and did so in the early part of 1862. He remained at the rank of private throughout the war, and received an honorable discharge on June 18, 1865.
Following his discharge, Edgerton opened a shoe store in Factoryville, New York. The shoe business failed the following year and he moved to Wisconsin. He entered Rush Medical School in Chicago and graduated fourth in his class in 1872. He established a practice in Fort Scott, Kansas for a brief time and then decided to become a country doctor in Wheeling, Missouri. He was married in 1876 and had three children.
After a series of personal tragedies and illnesses, he abandoned his medical practice and bought a general merchandise store in Wheeling, Missouri. He operated it profitably until 1889, at which time he became the president of the local bank. He also later served as Mayor of Wheeling. William Wilberforce Edgerton died on November 11, 1931.
Source
Brief unpublished fifteen page biography with collection file.
Scope and Contents
The William W. Edgerton collection is composed of personal correspondence between Civil War private William Wilberforce Edgerton of the 107th New York Volunteers and his immediate family. Most of the letters are between William W. Edgerton and his mother, Dorothy Doud Edgerton. Additional correspondents include his brother, John Howard Edgerton, and his sisters, Martha Newton and Augusta Tenney.
The correspondence is arranged chronologically. Following it are some battle diaries kept by William Edgerton, and some other miscellaneous items.
Note: Locations have been noted exactly as written even though obviously misspelled, e.g. staford for Stafford and corthouse for Courthouse.
Subjects (Persons)
Edgerton, William Wilbur
Subjects (Organizations)
107th New York Volunteers
Subjects
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Antietam, Battle of, Md., 1862; Chancellorsville, Battle of, Chancellorsville, Va., 1863; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition
This collection was donated by Mr. Owsley R. Welch ca. 1955.
Detailed Description
- (Box 1, 2, Folder 1-141)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Factoryville, NY, Feb. 9, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Factoryville, NY, June 6, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lowrey to Dorothy Edgerton, Waverly, NY, Aug. 29, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Maryland Heights, Oct. 23, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp near [Antietam Ford], Nov. 12, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, North Potsdam, NY, Nov. 30, 1862. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Verso William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp near Staford corthouse [Stafford, VA], Jan. 24, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Feb. 8, 186[3] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Feb. 25, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - William Edgerton to John Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Mar. 20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Mar. 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Aquia Landing, Apr. 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - William Edgerton to John Edgerton, Aquia Landing, Apr. 12, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Apr. 12, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Hopes Landing, Apr. 27, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Stafford Corthouse [Stafford, VA], Apr. 28, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Stafford corthouse [Stafford, VA], May 13, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Stafford corthouse [Stafford, VA], May 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Stafford corthouse, [Stafford, VA], May 19, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - William Edgeton to his father, Stafford corthouse [Stafford, VA], May 23-24, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Fairfax, VA], Jan. 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - William Edgerton to [Augusta Tenney or Martha Newton], Stafford corthouse [Stafford, VA], June 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Stafford corthouse [Stafford, VA], June 11, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Dumfries, [VA], June 14, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Leasburg, [VA], June 19-20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Harper's Ferry, July 17, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Warrinton Junction, [VA], July 27, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Warrinton Junction, [VA], July 29, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [VA], [ca. July 29, 1863] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Alice Woaters[?] to Oscar [brother] Pitt County, NC, June 14, 1863, Also M.E. Woaters to Oscar [son] (Letter found by William Edgerton on a Confederate soldier) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton. Kelleys ford, [VA], Aug. 1863 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford on the Bapahonac [VA], Aug. 4, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford [VA], Aug. 12, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford, VA, Aug. 14, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Kelleys ford [VA], Aug. 19, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - W.G.L. Brook to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp 107th NYV, Aug. 23, [1863] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - W.G.L. Brook to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp 107th NYV, Aug. 29, [1863] (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford, VA, Sep. 2, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Martha Newton to Augusta Tenney, Sparta [WI], Sep. 3, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford, VA, [Sep. 1863] (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Kelleys ford, VA, Sep. 9, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Kelleys ford, VA, Sep. 10, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Raccoon ford, VA, Sep. 17, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Raccoon ford, VA, Sep. 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Raccoon ford, [VA], Sep. 22, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Raccoon ford, VA, Sep. 23, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], [Raccoon ford, VA], Sep. 26, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Decherd Station, TN, Oct. 6, 1863, Oct. 8, 1863, Oct. 12, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - William Edgerton to Martha Newton, Camp 107 NYV, TN, Oct. 8, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Decherd, TN], Oct. 13, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Decherd, TN], Oct. 16, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Decherd, TN], Oct. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [between Murfreesboro, TN and Stevenson, AL], Oct. 29, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [between Murfreesboro, TN and Stevenson, AL], Nov. 17, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Nov. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp 107 NYV [TN], Dec. 5, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp 107 NYV [TN], Dec. 8, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp 107 NYV, TN, Dec. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [TN], Dec. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Dec. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Dec. 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [TN], Dec. 21, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Dec. 24, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Dec. 26, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Dec. 26, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [TN], Dec. 29, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Jan. 6, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Jan. 16, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Jan. 17, 1864, Jan. 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [TN], Jan. 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Bell Buckle Bridge, TN, Jan. 20, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Jan. 30, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 1, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 8, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Shelbyville, TN, Feb. 18, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Mar. 4, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 4, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 6, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 14, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 28, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Shelbyville, TN, Apr. 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], [Bridgeport, TN], Apr. 30, 1864 - May 21, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp on the Mar, May 17, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Dallas, GA], May 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Lost Mountain, GA [Dallas, GA], June 14, [1864] and June 15, [1864] (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Camp in the brestworks on the battlefield, GA, June 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Marietta, GA], June 23, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Marietta, GA], June 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [2 miles N. of Chattahoochee River], July 8, 1864, July 9, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Chattahoochee R., GA, July 12, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Chattahoochee River, GA, July 15, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], 10 miles SE of Atlanta, GA, July 19, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, [July 1864] (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - William Edgerton to [Dorothy or John Edgerton], [Atlanta, GA], July 24, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, July 29, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Camp in brest. in front of Atlanta, GA, Aug. 1, [1864] (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Wiliam Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Atlanta, GA, Aug. 13, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Atlanta, GA], Hospital 2 miles in the rear, Aug. 11, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], [Atlanta, GA] Hospital, Aug. 13, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, [Atlanta, GA] Hospital, Aug. 14, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Aug. 25, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Atlanta, GA, Aug. 25, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Chattahoochee Bridge, 5 miles from Atlanta, GA, Aug. 28, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Chattachoochee Bridge, GA, Aug. 31, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Sep. 4, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Sep. 9, 1864, Sep. 12, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Sep. 16, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Sep. 21, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Oct. 20, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Atlanta, GA, Oct. 29, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Angyle Island, Savannah River, Ga, Dec. 18, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Savannah, GA, Dec. 24, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Savannah, GA, Dec. 30, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - William Edgerton to [John Edgerton], Savannah, GA, Dec. 30, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Savannah, GA, Jan. 13, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Swamps of SC, Jan. 25, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Fayetteville, NC, Mar. 12, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Goldsboro, NC, Mar. 29, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - William Edgerton to Dorothy Edgerton, Factoryville [Near Waverly, NY], June 29, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, Dodge City, WI, July 5, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - William Edgerton to Augusta Tenney, Factoryville, NY, July 30, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, Dodge City, WI, Nov. 5, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Martha Newton to William Edgerton, Sparta, WI, Nov. 23, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, Oak Grove, Dodge City County, WI. Dec. 3, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, Oak Grove City, Dodge City County, WI, Dec. 26, [1865] (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Dorothy Edgerton to William Edgerton, [Oak Grove, Dodge City County, WI], Jan. 11, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Diary, Chapter 2, Battle of Antietam, Sep. 26, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Diary, Chapter 3, Nov. 25, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Diary, Chapter 4, Battle of Chancellorville, May 1, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Diary, Chapter 5, Battle of Gettysburg, Dec. 13, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Diary, Chapter 6, Battle of Gettysburg, July 3, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - William Edgerton letter fragment, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Calling card of Mr. & Mrs. Tenney; includes envelope [H. Augusta Tenney] (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - List of clothing drawn by William Edgerton, July 1863 - June 1864 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Camp Pass issued by E. P. Van Valkenburgh, Jan. 20, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Unidentifiable fragments of eight items (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Fragments of seven additional letters (Box 2, Folder 141)